welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
in particular I think that the
situational awareness of organizations
is taken for granted when it's actually
a really remarkable thing individuals
can make sense of circumstances
individuals can act how in the world can
information flow in an organization of
dozens hundreds or thousands of people
in a timely manner especially flow on
subjects that were never predicted in
the first place we never built or baked
into the structure now I'm not here
saying that you know something like a
natural disaster or the exact course of
a battle or the exact course of events
in an industrial accident aren't things
that are physically predictable they
certainly are but when people set up
bureaucratic structures they by default
can't foresee all the circumstances
there are too many cases you know
where's the special form for you know
the world is ending can you delay my
taxes by four months like there's no
form like that it would be ridiculous to
have a form like that
so whatever when it when the world the
end of the world comes which this is not
this is merely you know just this is
another historical plague the kovat
influenza is you know no worse than any
of those big historical events have been
it's not even as bad as the influence of
1918 however if the end of the world
were to come people instantly in a
bureaucracy even would jump from
bureaucratic coordination where you read
the piece of paper in front of you you
pursued the narrow task at hand to
something more informal right there
would be some designated perhaps chain
of command if it's a hierarchical
organization or there might be something
like extraordinary working groups set up
that had the authority to deal with the
specific issue so something that's
outside the hierarchy so the two
mechanisms at play one is much more
hierarchical military in nature where
essentially for unforeseen circumstances
you pass the buck up the chain of
command
so this would be how in a military
situation if there no standing orders
I'd unit my request for further
instructions just going up the chain all
the way to the theoretical you know
commander of the battlefield now
different militaries do this in
different ways there are different
philosophies of command and these have
changed law through the 19th and 20th
century the key puzzle people try to
solve is you know how to reduce the
decision burden at higher and higher
levels of command
because micromanaging the battlefield
like a real-time strategy game is simply
impossible even today today with digital
technologies you could possibly just
jump into any corner of the battlefield
and see what's happening there by camera
audio and so on but you're still a
single person you're still a single mind
you can't make all of these 290
decisions all over the place
even with something like information
processing such as machine learning I
think it's actually constrained by some
of the same features that constrained
bureaucratic reasoning all artificial
intelligence systems today that are in
wide use rely on big data they rely on a
vast training set of examples to make
sense of situations and often gave
anomalous and anomalously bad advice or
outcomes in fringe situations the reason
that an artificial intelligence can beat
a master go player today is because it
can play billions if not trillions of
games against itself every edge case
suddenly is not this rare unitary event
but something with thousands tens of
thousands millions of instances of that
exact case playing out in various minut
details and bearings a bureaucracy is
best suited to dealing with something
that happens a hundred or a thousand or
ten thousand times in a year
it is worse suited to deal with
something that happens once a year or
even worse something that happened it's
once every 50 years and artificial
intelligence is actually in a way worse
it's very good at dealing with
thing that happens a thousand or 10,000
times per second now because of this
even on the modern battlefield the
artificial intelligence while helpful
can't necessarily make sense of
everything that's happening nor can a
general make sense of everything that's
happening so since you know I think this
was early 20th century or actually no I
think it's 19th century the Prussian
General Staff and modern descended
militaries have had this directive you
have an overriding objective as a local
commander we won't tell you how to do it
you're just empowered to do whatever is
necessary right so there are in fact in
a chain
not just of strict obedience of orders
but a chain of judgement calls going up
the hierarchy and the quality of that
chain of judgment calls whether I defer
this up whether I tend to solve it
myself and how exactly do I solve it
then depends on the quality of the
people in the chain and that's
inescapable no process new procedure is
going to abate that now in non-military
contexts you often have a very similar
situation such as the organization of
the people who were helping to build the
big concrete sarcophagus that now exists
around the Chernobyl power plant town
and I just have a show of hands of if
people know what I'm talking about
people know enough about the Chernobyl
disaster okay
well in that case I'll just summarize it
in one sentence but I'm glad everyone
knows basically trembled her plan was a
nuclear power plant meltdown in the
1980s and one of the efforts to help
deal with the disaster was simply bury
the whole thing under concrete however
you know this open reactor with an open
nuclear fire right it was just a fire it
was constantly emitting radioactive
particles as the reactor itself had
melted down was very hazardous work
especially initially and it was
hazardous you know up to the point of
many of the people working on a dying
some were volunteers so
order to do it it was an improvised
group it wasn't just a military group
but during that period of work where
every command or judgment called mic
mean another worker is dead or another
worker lives you know one becomes you
know a hero of the Soviet Union after
death and the other one might enjoy
their medal enjoy that in that situation
they they had this chain of judgment
calls locally right now I've described
in detail the sort of chain of command
structure this kind of military
structure and logic I try to sketch out
an argument for why I think artificial
intelligence does not remove the need
for it because it's bad at dealing at
outlier events so we have to maintain
human judgement there now let's talk
about informal working group now let's
talk about working groups organizations
can sometimes achieve situational
awareness because they understand that
no actually even if we have good
judgment calls even if our processes
were somehow sufficient we just are not
built for this
yet our organization as a whole is
expected to do something about this and
in that case you go through your entire
staff you don't necessarily think about
seniority you don't necessarily you know
think about what the normal channels of
command are and you build a parallel
structure if you are very lucky and if
you're operating in a culture of high
integrity and honesty you can appoint
something like the committee to truly
solve a problem but as we know the
federal government or any corporate
organization is filled with committees
and subcommittees that function more as
reputation laundering reputation
laundering factories these like avoid
responsibility rather than taking
actions but the reason it's leather
littered with committees is the
following the failure case demonstrates
the use case an organization is expected
to do something that its normal
bureaucratic structures hierarchical
structures do not handle the leadership
either does not wish to handle it or
wishes to Handlen says
you know this is not a normal problem
we're gonna resort to extraordinary
means we're gonna have an investigative
committee into this or we're gonna have
a committee deal with it and then that
committee is composed allegedly on the
basis of expertise so in an interesting
way in a deep sociological sense the
chain of command and hierarchy is
implicitly resting on individual
authority meanwhile the committee
structure rests implicitly on knowledge
right
supposedly technical expertise sometimes
disinterest if we go all the way to a
legal court but that's not really
necessary you can have an interested
committee the committee might recall the
board for example right it would be
silly if I if a board had no stake in
the company it was managing so there's
in fact variation interest versus
disinterest so if I would say the true
fundamental claim there is is knowledge
and that there is of course a
distinction between knowledge and
judgment right knowledge we held
collectively I think judgment cannot be
held collectively as comes up to being a
single Minds decision eventually now
there are some interesting prerequisites
for making committees work I think that
it they require a high degree of
professionalism where my professionalism
I don't mean just a code of etiquette
when you go see your doctor you know
you're not Bob and the doctor is not
Alice you are the patient and the doctor
is a doctor and all of us know how that
interaction is supposed to look to a
lesser extent we all know how
relationship between a client and lawyer
work right the reason is not because we
intricately understands the circuits not
because we introduced and the detail of
them as human beings it's because we
understand what a functional social role
is supposed to be now the social role
might not be quite as functional but we
understand what it's supposed to look
like it could be that in a society the
relation between doctor and patient is
you know it's it's it's dysfunctional
perhaps it causes a lot of misdiagnosis
or something however everyone in this
society understands
how to play those roles now there should
be an understanding that if you are
appointed to investigate something
extraordinary professionalism and your
LARP expects you you know there's a
Larkin district the doctor is Larkin
short for live-action roleplay you are
role-playing that you are not Alice and
not Bob rather you are a doctor and a
patient you don't need to understand the
intricate details of each other to
interact and get the business of the day
done and I think for a committee member
well when they're wearing their hat as
the committee member and this body has
been assembled temporarily or
permanently to make decisions you have
to actually not think of your interests
in the old hierarchy and the old
bureaucratic process where bureaucratic
processes again this breaking down of
tasks of a complicated world look into a
series of simple scripts right one way
to think of a highly bureaucratized
environment is that it's almost a piece
of software where pieces of code are
executed by all the individuals stacked
neatly into it into a role a lot of
things we might think of as
non-bureaucratic are actually
bureaucratic for example the assembly
line highly bureaucratic in this usage
of the word because you know when I you
know put in the door and the car rolls a
little bit further and someone puts in
the windows into the door I don't think
for necessarily know everything about
the construction of the car I know what
my job is and I do that part I'm not
taking responsibility as a craftsman
would to build the entire car it's much
more economical for me to just take
responsibility for I will put this door
in now whether the car is any good
whether the assembly line is efficient
that's really not my problem in a
similar way you know I'm just filling
out the a40 form and whether the you
know whether my federal agency or my
company are doing the right thing or
doing well in a sense that's not really
my responsibility so one has to exit
that mindset so if you're pulled from
the assembly line are pulled from the
bureaucratic structure and placed into
such a body you suddenly have to be
proactively investigating seeking
knowledge and presenting it to fellow
committee members to reach a natural
decision that's the first prerequisite
this professionalism is very emotionally
and intellectually challenging because
it puts you out of the default role
secondly the functionality has to be at
the peak of the organization where the
existing structure mustn't see any
decision you reach as illegitimate the
body has to both in theory and practice
have decision-making ability and
whatever the internal structure of this
organization is the government
non-government organized religion it has
to be tolerant of that decision-making
process now this is easier said than
done right you might have say a
government where you create a
consultative body and before you note it
you know it the consultative body has
the real power and you've been removed
from power
most politic in power will avoid this
outcome some very farsighted people
might decide this is a good outcome
because they fear that they will fail
succession problems if I'm being a
little flippant and if I'm simplifying
it a little bit the evolution of the
English Parliament was very much like
this a consultative body becoming a true
legislative body becoming eventually a
ruling body with even executive power is
being vested in the hands of a new
office Prime Minister selected from
among parliamentarians now of course
Prime Minister the prime ministerial
office itself is no longer a committee
but still committees are these very
powerful objects partially because they
can make sense of unusual circumstances
they can be hollowed out in a second way
so one of them is being overridden by an
existing power structure the other one
is bureaucratization where instead of it
being say you know if you inflate the
committee massively it is in terms of
social technology basically the same
thing as a Senate or as a Congress or as
a parliament in a smaller size it could
be a group of four or five friends
behind a table making sense of things
it gets harder and harder to manage and
keep functional the larger it is but
with additional social technologies such
as expectation of public honesty such as
investment in a direct persuasive
ability rather than persuasion of the
audience you can scale it to maybe
hungry people or maybe even 200 people
we need to understand that you know the
parliaments and congresses of the 19th
and 18th century were not like the
Congress's in Parliament's of today it
was essentially 200 of the country's
most powerful and wealthy people
gathered in a room deciding what to do
one would make a speech and the speech
would not persuade the country or
persuade the other congressmen when's
the last time that you saw a congressman
in the u.s. changed their vote on the
basis of either rhetoric or a logical
argument delivered on you know the floor
I think it's just not been it's not been
in our lifetimes but it did once exist
and perhaps existed at a higher level in
British Parliament then I'd say they did
in French Parliament terrorism or
possibly even later Congress's of the
u.s. it certainly was therefore the
original Continental Congress and you
know for the gathering in Philadelphia
when the Constitutional set up all of
these things that today are read as
these you know intellectual artifact the
Federalist Papers the anti federalist
papers all of that stuff that was just
part of practical political debate can
you imagine anything of substance coming
out of practical political debate
between Republicans and Democrats today
and even the fact that there are
Republicans and Democrats shows
something interesting it shows that you
have perhaps a poorly functioning but a
hierarchical command and control
structure that determines the vote in
this sense it's debatable with their
Congress even is a true committee in the
sense that I was talking about
committees earlier so bureaucratize
ation procedural ization and new
hierarchies can overrule the committee
body can cause it dysfunction can
disassemble it so you have to allow for
it
now dealing with disasters we then have
always the suspension of bureaucracy
followed by a you know a a chain of
judgment if it's highly functional and a
chain of merely controlling action if
it's a little bit dysfunctional so
hierarchical structure we can have a
committee and there is a third option
yes there is a third option the third
option is a relatively high trust
environment with informal social ties
these can of course be used for
corruption corruption you might mean not
following the rules but you know the
difference in not following the rules
when it's corruption and when it's
common sense is merely in whether it's
good or judged good by society at large
or by the interests of the organization
ideally both right it's both legal its
moral and it's good for the organization
if you are you know harassed for
violating the rules in such a way that
is morally good practically good and
good for the organization you know I
think I think you're that's that's more
corrupt almost then being simply
forgiven or and of course after the fact
that rules should be changed to account
for this to make it more legible to
others and to not provide a cover for
you know action it's essentially
anti-social I think that that final step
of a high trust culture where there are
friendships all over the hierarchy all
over these procedure alized assembly
lines of paper all over these sometimes
functioning and non functioning
committees represents an actually
distributed network of information
sharing and yes also influenced and is
in a way this most natural human
organizing system right we've always
lived in tribes we've always been a
social species we know how far gossip
can travel now it seems gossip mostly
travels about you know who we're the
mates are and where the food is but
we've applied that to many diverse
circumstances so you know despite these
these
these impulses perhaps originally
evolving for very primitive means they
can have very sophisticated application
but you know this network is as good at
bypassing functioning things as it is at
bypassing dysfunctional dysfunctional
things say the biggest enemy of the
secrecy of the Manhattan Project during
World War two was in fact precisely not
any targeted process of infiltration by
say the Soviet government or the Nazi
the Nazi government the biggest enemy
was simply people like to talk to their
friends about what they're doing and
what's going wrong and what's going
right and you know there are people who
know that you have to listen when
dissatisfied employees go around and
discuss what's going on so this sort of
new rumor mill and rumor spread was what
was most easily picked up by
intelligence agents from Germany it was
much harder to just have an embedded
agent in the project though that's
certainly possible right the Soviets
achieved one or two examples achieve
this and one or two examples so yeah
situational awareness can be achieved
through these three methods and now I'm
looking forward to the questions very
cool so if you have a question for Sam
oh just write it in the chat box
indicate if you want me to read on your
behalf I'll warm up sam'l with a few
questions myself so what came to mind is
this how you ended this really good
article you wrote in the American mind
and I'm gonna read it the last paragraph
the time has come in America once again
for heroism don't worry about
credentials or prestige don't worry
about party affiliation find the brave
and the smart and hand them the keys to
the ignition as fast as you can your
bars your boss can fire them later if
need be and yes maybe he will fire you
too who can afford to care about job
security in a plague love it and yes I
just want maybe give any additional
thoughts on that and I have a question
the follow-up well that article is
nearly a month old and at the start of
the article I was unfortunately there's
a less elated you know
a less positive a less you know
interesting line where I said that in a
few months there will be tens of
thousands of dead Americans and some
people who read this or like some are
you really comfortable making that
prediction and I very much was
comfortable making that prediction so I
had assumed the hierarchical structure
of the CDC had failed I had assumed that
the executive structure of the US had
failed so it was not care you know the
presidency was not going to effectively
handle an extraordinary situation though
arguably that's one of its functions I
certainly was not expecting intervention
at a government or non-government level
so the fastest intervention that can
work with a six day doubling time right
even though of course in the wild an
exponential is never an exponential it's
always broken by some things right I
still think you know the doubling time
of six days was very instructive in
optimal conditions you might have it you
know the number of infected might be
doubled every six days in such
circumstances I don't think bringing
together committees or the informal
network of influence and information are
fast enough so what I thought should be
done is individuals should be appointed
just with the authority to handle this
specific issue and no other and rule
should be suspended so they can do what
need to be and bring together whichever
agencies need to be brought together to
do particular steps to you know do
things such as if it's the right move to
acquire a lot of ventilators do that and
one of the requirements for such a
person to have good judgment was
actually an overlap good judgment and
knowledge right so they actually have to
be they actually have to be
knowledgeable right they have to be
smart and brave because timidity I think
is like one of the great curses of
people with knowledge especially today
because in many ways there is a negative
selection for it right sometimes in many
positions throughout say government and
society today being strategically
ignorant of what is in convene
- no actually reduces your
organization's liability right so that
needed to be like firmly bypassed
because in the u.s. you know perhaps
more similar to China than would be
comfortable testing was not readily
available and perhaps it was you know a
disaster
perhaps it simply was that no one was
prepared or simply they didn't want the
numbers to be too high at least at first
they wouldn't didn't want to panic
people and I think the second
interpretation that they just didn't
want to panic people and were
downplaying it by by limiting D testing
I think that's quite plausible hmm and
the word that was really salient for me
was heroism and then your distinction
about live player dead player came to
mind as well and I really loved that
distinction so maybe you could elaborate
what that means and when I feel into
that and reflect on that distinction
virtue comes to mind as you know
stoicism is about living a life of
virtue so maybe you can kind of
elaborate on what that distinction is
and maybe how being a life player
relates to being virtuous um well the
distinction I introduced known by
articles between you know life and death
players is the distinction is the
distinction between someone that is
following a script a preset pattern of
behavior and someone that is adapting
actively that is adapting creatively to
completely new circumstances they've
never encountered a dead player in a
strategic sense might be an individual
or organization that however highly
effective has this limited repertoire of
responses a live player will attempt
things sometimes in a very costly way
that have never been done before so you
might have you know a highly effective
dead player a simple a simple script of
moves on the chess board that you are
supposed to take you know if then
sentences essentially and a live player
might still be relatively bad at winning
a chess game against such an automated
system or script
player but life players become over
there are over the long term the most
robust to change because unpredicted
things always happen narrow
optimizations are revealed to be narrow
so stuff that lasts longer individuals
that adapt more dynamically to
disruptions that that's sort of in the
direction of life players now for an
individual to be a live player I think
it requires several virtues one of the
things is bravery or I think one of the
basic flaws of you know human human
thinking is that we often don't want to
know that we don't know we are often
afraid of changes unpredictable
unpredictability risks a live player
consciously understands risks entered it
and undertakes those risks you know if
you ever feel that you are completely
safe in a way not in a deep
philosophical but just in a practical
way completely insulated from financial
you know interpersonal health risks it's
very likely that you're overloaded on
risk it's likely or that you're not
paying conscious attention to all the
ways in which you are risk-taking rather
than door you know pushing that into the
background into out of awareness you
know if your control panel all the
lights are blinking green there are two
possibilities one is everything as well
and the other one is your control panel
is broken right and you know this is
it's the case that there seems to be
some type of self-deception here and it
can be addressed partially through
bravery through sort of not being afraid
of realities as they exist if I
emphasize a broadsheet diner another one
might be self honesty again where you
don't necessarily you don't focus on the
gains that fortunately or unfortunately
being strategically ignorant can bring
you and you choose to embrace knowledge
even when someone costly
and I think number three would be being
capable of living sustain society
without being that constrained by
societal norms let me explain
following the inner logic of the
societal norms rather than the letter so
the spirit rather than the letter of the
social interpersonal moral societal
political religious law of whatever
society you happen to find yourself in
because the fact is if you are incapable
of doing that right if you're incapable
of mostly following that spirit and you
follow up followed the letter you can
still live fine but if you are incapable
of following the letter whether or not
the letter is correct the rest of
society does punish you right so you
know I think it's Aristotle said that
anyone who lives alone is either beast
or God right so we all live in society
or mostly people not most of us have not
you know ascended to godhood or you know
go on to become a beast a solitary
creature and because of that we have to
have a way to deal with the rest of
society whether it's right and wrong and
ideally we understand the positive
spirit behind what can be done rather
than merely follow rules but if we don't
understand the spirit following the
rules is what allows us to live together
hopefully that answers your question
there's a good question I think yeah and
it answers it nicely and it maps over
the cardinal virtues with any stoic
where the salt would follow so Daniel if
you're gonna meet yourself in s-sama
your question yeah I'm I'm still
processing what you just said because
I'm starting to think that to some
extent due to social isolation people
have been pushed one or two notches
closer to the beast or the god end of
the spectrum and my question has
something to do with that I feel there's
maybe this latent potential energy in
society right now that doesn't really
know where it it needs to go i framed it
based on what you said earlier
when you force people to work from home
this partially breaks the myth of their
roles and their professionalism and it
reduces our LARPing tendencies so I
guess just generally what sort of
opportunities do you see emerging from
that I think what I would be most
hopeful of is a culture of I will do
what I can do and I will be acknowledged
for doing what I can do where we go one
click away from procedure alized
procedure lights distribution of tasks
where it's my job to put the door in the
car and it doesn't matter if the car
already has an engine or not - I'm
taking responsibility for not
necessarily the whole car but you know
the safety of this door and I'm also
taking responsibility for spotting what
is wrong if anything is wrong and going
to talk to the engine guys and ask them
should we stop the assembly line there
seems to be no engine in this car I
think our society is too mechanistic and
too bureaucratized overall the way it's
currently structured for us to go more
than a few clicks in the direction of
personal judgement and responsibility
taking where I have to say something
when I say responsibility taking I'm not
saying that it's always upon the
individual to take responsibility I'm
also saying we need a society that can
accept an individual's claim to
responsibility and respect it right
without that part we can do all the
inner psychological work that we want
have all the virtue we want but still
the virtue comes to be punished
essentially either through lack of
opportunity or through just even more
active measures right which is why in
the essay the annoyance or Armageddon
essay that Peter cited I had
straightforwardly said yes your boss
might fire the exceptional person you
hired when the crisis is over and yes
they might fire you so I'm saying yes
you're gonna have to internalize the
cost I'm not saying yes you should
should have internalize the cost but
whether or not it was you know your duty
to internalize the cost or not
such as you know that that's the way the
cards have been dealt to us in society I
think so I would say that the upward
potential then is capped by the very
mechanistic structure of the
bureaucracies and the limited ability of
culture especially a company company
culture or culture to accept the taking
of personal responsibility right where
it's seen as initiating a turf war
essentially almost always I think that
limits it it a little bit I think that
there is a lot of opportunity for people
to Unger sleight themselves in the land
so I think there will be a lot of people
who if they are in an economically
privileged position already will realize
that they are unhappy with their job in
important ways and will quit and find
something else hopefully something more
productive possibly even decide to
create new things but again I do have to
emphasize this is you know a smaller
class of society the class of society
that can afford leisure for most people
you know do if they lose their job right
now they will have to find another job
and this you know space for reflection
personal growth personally driven
creation is notably undercut by those
circumstances at least in practice like
in theory I think or for particular
individuals for outliers you can
definitely even under the conditions of
you know economic deprivation achieve
such results and find and figure out new
ways in which you can deploy your
judgment and perhaps find a better
hierarchy of judgment to work in than
the current one but I'm just saying you
know which outcomes I I think we'll see
you won't see I also think remote work
is unfortunately going to be followed by
remote surveillance so I think what's
gonna happen is instead of us allowing
workers to work on their own matters at
home what's actually going to happen is
everyone's going to accept that if they
were working remotely
your boss has spyware installed on your
computer
but only during work hours however how
many jobs have we had where the work
hours are perhaps significantly fake and
to stay saying you have to do some non
work things while plausibly pretending
to work I think that a lot of the jobs
in in an industrial economy are like
this unfortunately so the click will
then be surveillance will move from the
office to you know your laptop and most
people I know they use their work
laptops for personal stuff - right and
the observation at home will suddenly be
normalized so that's a negative outcome
and that's more societal than individual
but I hope I answered your question
Daniel yeah you uh you put put some
names to my fears thank you Samuel are
you good to stay about ten minutes after
the hour yes okay because we had a lot
of good questions so if anyone has to
leave they can leave any time they want
this will be recorded and posted on on
YouTube
Yoshio would you like to unmute yourself
and ask your question trend qualitative
quantitative risk management and safety
culture institutions I mean it's
paralleled in society as well safety
culture but is also prevalent in
institutions are there similar
criticisms between safety culture in
society and in institutions well
cultures can definitely have cultures
can have different safety settings right
different safety cultures you know I
think looking at Japan and comparing
Japan to Italy or to India or to Britain
you're gonna find some very different
defaults that pervade all of society
if you have a lost object the object is
notably more likely to be returned if
you are in a public space mask-wearing
is completely normal and normalized I
think in the West if someone's wearing a
mask whether they have a cold or a flu
knot you're talking about deadly
influenza I'm just talking about
everyday elements it's considered
strange that you're wearing a mask it's
unusual what you have to hide in a lot
of East Asian societies the norm is more
like oh you're probably sick and you're
trying to keep us safe or if it's China
it's like yeah I know the air pollution
is really bad it causes me breathing
problems too it's fine
so I think in Japan the air is fairly
clean at least for now well you know
western-style industrial society so I
think the people are wearing masks
implicitly to protect others and I think
this is culturally understood
additionally it's a you know it's it's
understood that if you see an object in
US you know this is less good for
disease spread you should not be
touching strange things you don't know
where they are but there's a pro-social
element where it routinely happens that
you know children might lose small
completely irrelevant toys in say a
supermarket or something and yet these
are brought to the lost-and-found desk
like that expects that is interesting it
suggests that the belief is that the
level of trust the level of trust is so
high that it's worthwhile to say to find
to bring something to the lost and found
or go check to the lost and found
because both the person seeking for the
lost item and the person finding the
item they both believe that they'll do
what they're supposed to do right so
it's worthwhile to go to lost and found
versus buying the kid another toy
because you have such high expectations
of the behavior of your fellow citizens
so I think that's a direct analogy of
safety culture I'm also gonna say
another thing when the Fukushima power
plant you know accident disaster you
might call it
and there were a lot of calls from the
elderly who were previously workers at
power plants at nuclear power plants who
volunteered for the hazardous work there
that is a remarkably high level of
social conscientiousness and that's
because I think despite all the issues
of having a structurally old society the
elderly in Japan are loved and respected
but also they the elderly themselves
think of the rest of society as their
children their grandchildren their true
responsibilities so the level of overall
orientation is there's a nice mutualism
between generations and I think in the
u.s. unfortunately the level of
mutualism is low you know I will say
it's higher than people think there was
a lot of you know online there was a lot
of negativity about say boomers versus
Millennials are now sumers Gen Z but I
think that no one wants their grandma to
die
no one wants their dad today so people
are trying to do the right thing
during the co-ed crisis we don't do as
much of the right thing as we could do
in Japan or perhaps they're doing in
Israel we're in Israel what happened was
a lot of the very young conscripts they
have a concept system people who are 19
or 20 sometimes I think even teenagers
have been sort of you know conscripted
and are now working various jobs that
are related to keeping spaces sanitary
or taking care of the sick because they
themselves you know even if they lack
the right medical training are basically
you know they're gonna be fine they're
not going to die they're not going to be
permanently scarred unless they have
some particular condition like the death
rate is really low for people under 20
as is the complication rate from what is
known so that's an inverse right in
Japan during Mishima the elderly
volunteer and are used to work in these
ways and the rest of society honors
their sacrifice because it's understood
that you know the reproductive damage
comes first from radiation so if you're
exposed to a lot of radiation your first
biggest risk
is birth defects for your children your
second risk is cancer but cancer takes
five to ten years to develop okay
your third risk is super high doses when
your teeth start falling out and your
hair starts falling out but these levels
of exposure you know the elderly are in
theory better off for number one and to
a lesser extent even number two because
the total amount of cut lifespan is
going to be four or five years instead
of say forty or fifty years if you
develop cancer at different stages in
your life though it can be fair
depending on the type of a cancer a
younger person might have an easier time
surviving chemotherapy and so on the
details and the realities of the
particular challenge matters such as
young people's resistance to kovat if
that's not true then it's foolish to
expose basically young adults but in
another way isn't that like you know the
openness and the willingness to have
young people engage in direct pro-social
action or the elderly engage in direct
prosocial action that's like that is
safety culture - I think in America it's
hyper individualist
so we're uncomfortable with being like
well you know this portion of society by
chance or Nature has an opportunity to
do something good here and perhaps
engage in some amount of sacrifice do we
allow them to do it I think there's a
discomfort of saying yeah any particular
demographic is now allowed to do this or
even implicitly expect it to do this I
think we um we don't like to think about
it in those terms so these are more one
step away from your question but I think
this is the closest I can think of
something like safety culture share to a
whole society but uh yeah cool cool ahem
you have a question yes thanks Peter hi
Sam oh good to see you
yeah good to see you too
[Music]
when you were talking earlier about the
different sorts of authority structures
and their transformations and evolutions
I was wondering if you had considered
the relationship of those sorts of
transformations to any cyclical
of history or cyclical theories of
governance in particular the one that
came to mind was was eben Hal dune but
perhaps other other cyclical theories
like Stranglers just curious if you've
given any thought to those sorts of
dynamics yes the dynamics are describing
our more organizational than
society-wide
but I think there's certainly you know
there's certainly society-wide cycles
I think the ancient Greek concept of the
key class was interesting which was
studied both by Polybius and Aristotle
which proposed that the forms of
government go in a cycle right and
Aristotle and Plato's rendition I think
it starts off you know there's there's
like you know there's monarchy the turns
into tyranny is overthrown by
aristocracy that turns into all of our
key that then becomes a democracy but
then ends up being a dysfunctional
tyrannical democracy and then the cycle
restarts you you're right back to the
setup of a tyranny or a monarchy this
was based on the observation of the
dynamics and you know hundreds of Greek
city-states in their time period which
are you know it's an interesting
political science experiment isn't it
many cities that are all you know
they're in the business of growing wine
during the business of growing olives
and you know harnessing harnessing them
for olive oil they're doing fishing in a
way it's like a very good control trial
all of these random little Greek
city-states all around the Mediterranean
having about the same type of economy
but at different stages of political
evolution so I wouldn't dismiss those
insights out right I will say though
that it's very difficult to distinguish
different cyclical theories of history
from each other safe Spengler's right
because we've only had one history so
far right we we have not we do not have
10 or 50,000 years of recorded history
we'll only have something like four or
five thousand years of recorded history
any sort of cyclical development might
just be outside of a review and
cycle on the 10,000 year time scale you
know if i evoke some association to the
to the long now foundation where I also
have a position is not something that we
can yet observe shorter cycles on about
a thousand years we can observe and we
can talk about but it's harder to get
the confounding factors out right it's
harder to say well okay this society
basically transitioned into an
extractive mode of production we're
continuously undermine to say its own
economic productivity or continuously
undermined its own ability to reproduce
the population it's hard to distinguish
that explanation from well the climate
shifted and you know the the growing
season was shorter right it's very hard
to distinguish those two because those
two will usually coincide right the we
natural induces scarcity and natural
induced scarcity will then be followed
by additional artificial scarcity hope
that uh
somewhat answers the questions Kaleem
cool so maybe we'll sneak in one more
Jason would you like to read your
question can we make a distinction
between and safety culture versus a
culture of responsibility given that
health and safety has become the
principle next mechanism of
infantilization in our society yeah I
think that the point about
infantilization through medicalization
is interesting I would also point out
that the medicalization of issues is
often an authority grab or a power grab
pretty straightforwardly there's some
extreme examples like you saw in the
Soviet Union there used to exist a
psychiatric diagnosis called sluggishly
progressing schizophrenia so the she's
progressing schizophrenia had two
symptoms one was you're questioning the
rule of the Communist Party number two
is you might not yet have any other
symptoms of schizophrenia
but we'll put you under six-month
observation in a psychiatric ward I'm
just going to point out there's a dark
Beauty to what I just described think of
how much more elegant that is to get rid
of a dissident than say putting them in
a gulag you put them in a gulag you're
gonna write these tearful terrible
moving memoirs and they new or you're
gonna martyr them you declare them
schizophrenic well it becomes dubious
right someone would be have you read
this interesting psalmist thought and
someone else has said oh I thought he
was locked up in the loony bin and the
other person is like no no no the
communist party caused that to happen
the terrible part about this is you know
the person might actually be a
schizophrenic right if you worry
you know communist Russia 1982 and yours
it's the phrenic do you have delusions
of persecution from the Communist Party
you might even though there is real
persecution happening that's an extreme
case hopper and mental health is always
questionable so a lot of what I would
question in our own society is the over
diagnosis of depression where what I do
believe is there are many people who are
feeling miserable and having have a lack
of meaning in their life but I believe
we tend to pretend that this is some
mysterious society-wide
mental health crisis rather than perhaps
society has structurally made life ugly
and unlivable for significant portions
of the population so the medicalised
response is very interesting it is a
response of the authorities to you as an
individual rather than perhaps a
response of the authorities with society
or even the authorities with society
right and another one is medicalization
implies you should internalize the costs
and listen to someone outside of you
versus you know a more creative or
collaborative frame where actually you
should internalize the costs and you're
the ultimate decision-maker or we should
externalise some of the costs and
decision making is made together or
perhaps at least you know you
being told what to do but you're also
not paying the price of what you're
being told what to do right so you could
also have a social contract that goes
more in that direction and that's been
attempted by some of those some of those
countries so I think that safety culture
versus responsibility culture I think
you know you can never have a
bureaucratic rule set that covers all
details all functional safety cultures
have to be responsibilities cultures
unless you have a bias towards it is my
responsibility
there is no accident here or there is no
disaster here it will be much too easy
for events to slip through where it's no
one's responsibility to make it go well
so it's better to have an overly
developed sense of responsibility
proactively fix things and be grateful
to others when others proactively fix a
problem you were supposed to fix and
have it be that them doing that is not
bad for you that I think is the only way
to develop a real safety culture either
in an organization or in society at
large all right so I think that's a good
point to end
I'll make some closing announcements in
a moment but Sam oh do you have any
closing thoughts anything you'd like to
leave us with today well I was very
grateful for the thoughtful questions I
think that one of the things that's
often neglected is the overlap of the
personal emotional life with the social
interpersonal life of small scale with
the large institutionalized life in
society right things like hospitals
prisons governments they shape water
cooler conversations families you know
church communities these shape the
individual emotional life of people and
what motivates them and how they go
through life the full stack of these
developments that's something I really
hope we can all think about more and
integrate more in our public discourse
rather than chop it up into you know
mental health or economics or political
science or philosophy if you neatly pack
philosophy or political science for
economics into its own little box well
it's very hard to be a live player then
right like we can only have dead players
we can only operate off of narrow
recommendations of scripts rather than
pursuing holistic answers right right so
I'll only some closing thoughts
announcements in a moment but Sam oh
thanks so much for coming on my friend
that was a lovely chat and some great
Q&A and I was just messaging someone
privately in the chat box saying I love
Sam Lowe's mind so I'd love to have you
come back in the store and do another
session the plug a couple of events
coming up tonight at 7:00 p.m. Eastern
Time we have the narcissistic spotlight
so we're doing this artistic kind of
therapeutic blur the line between the
two experiment to address our narcissism
and shine some love on it one this
Friday that might be of interest to this
audience our buddy Patrick Ryan is
coming in samo at 8:30 Eastern Time
about trauma drama and I'll read the
blurb Patrick Ryan will deliver a
presentation on how trauma doesn't just
propagate but also scales and filters so
that turns you on
then I repeated that on the website
raven if you're still in the chat could
you if you want to have a campfire so
you're totally welcome great and the
stoah is a gift for all of us to freely
use and this time of need if you're
inspired to give a gift of the stoah
just go to this website
the stove's CA / gift and you can find
more information there all right thanks
everyone for coming today thank you
again for hosting Peter goodbye